welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
so everyone hi it's great to see you
welcome to the store the store is a
place for us to hear to hear and
dialogue about what matters most at the
knife's edge of this moment or so I'm
told and welcome to Chapel perilous
Chapel perilous is a space where we
trained to face the uncertainties of the
world where we push the boundaries of
who we are and how we think so it fits
in real the perfectly here at the store
so I see Chapel perilous I was talking a
little bit about this last week but I've
I've had time to think about it now and
I conceived of this space as a space
where we address one of the core
problems that we as humans have and it's
one of those problems that we don't look
at directly because it's bit
intimidating a bit scary perhaps but
once you notice that you see it
everywhere I think that problem is
intolerance of uncertainty and like I
said once you start looking for it there
it is you see people so certain they're
right that they're absolute dicks to
each other on the internet and in real
life sometimes you see all sorts of
individual psychological neuroses and
then there's this big you know
society-wide existential meaning crisis
it seems to be going around but for me
it's personal I'm one of those people
who really likes to be in control of
things I like things to make sense I
like order I like I like control and I
know this is not a realistic way to live
my life obviously because the world
isn't under my control and often it
doesn't seem to make much sense but I
didn't realise quite how unflattering
this sort of perspective looked on me
until I heard myself described in the
pages of Peter's diary well on his
online journal I'll keep what I read in
his private Diaries private see he
described people like me as a
rationalist to ameliorate their anxiety
through control yeah that's done he
didn't say people like Rebecca but
that's how I interpreted it because I'm
a masochist so I decided I need a place
to work on this I need a place to sort
of integrate those classic lessons from
the Stoics that sounds so good when you
read them so but does actually bring
them into my
if they thought psycho technologies that
reduce my intolerance to uncertainty
things would be a lot easier to deal
with and of course I need people to go
on this journey with because it's hard
to do these things alone so that's that
you guys I mean this is us and this is
Chapel perilous as I said this is like
it's something that I've been mulling
over for a while but the term travel
Paris only popped into my head a
fortnight ago so I've been going on this
sort of you know like a corkboard
adventure I don't actually have a
corkboard out but that's what's going on
in my head the court with all the string
and the pins and everything so I'm gonna
take you through what I figured out so
far about what chapel palaces and I'll
start with the history of the term that
kind of makes sense to me and I hope it
makes sense to you guys at least a
little bit of sense let's see if I can
show you what I've been up to what I've
been thinking about here we go you guys
can all see that right that is the wild
wood and the wild wood is a term that is
used to describe Britain's primary
forests so the primary forests are you
know those ones that have been there
ever since the beginning I suppose and
that's where all those classic Grail
romances are so anything Arthurian
that's all set in the world or it's
sometimes called the waste forest I
prefer the term wild wood and the first
time Chappell perilous turns up is in
one of these Grail romances and it's
it's a hero and they're all these
stories like mirror each other so it's
many heroes really this journey has been
taken many times but it's a hero going
on his quest for the ground he's going
through the wild wood and it's dense and
it's scary and the thing about the wild
wood is its intimidating because you
don't know what might be behind any
particular treaty just imagine a super
dense forest and of course because it's
one of those old stories it's a dark and
stormy night so he has to seek shelter
in this Chapel and he goes into the
chapel think he whew I'm in the chapel
now everything's fine unfortunately not
so he sees in the dim light in a
flickering candle light he sees as a
dead body later on the altar and then
just as he starts to back away from the
body the guttering candle light is
extinguished by
these blackened hands reaching in
through the windows and cutting out all
the candles and suddenly he's in the
dark and the sound just this moaning
intense sound and they're shifting
around on the dead body on the altar and
it's just terrifying thankfully that's
not our chapel paradise but do you think
it's interesting that this turns up in
Grail quests because real quests I mean
malaises all sorts of things we often
think if it is linked to you know Jesus
and stuff but actually there are stories
where it's not anything to do with
religion but I do think it kind of
represents the old certainties like
religion like the idea of a natural
order like the idea that there's one
true king who'll come back and make
everything right again it represents
certainty and that's often what
religions promised to give us nothing I
mean Scientology is actually called the
religion of certainty or the science of
certainty I think they call it that's
what a lot of people are trying to sell
to us when I start certainty maybe we
could think of those old certainties
that become a bit destabilize now a sort
of grail like because reason the reason
why I say this is because the next time
I find on my internet journey
researching Chapel parents and trying to
figure out what we're doing here is in
TS Eliot's the wasteland so this is 1922
obviously I read you the relevant stanza
to give you an idea of his vision of
chapel perilous in this decayed hold
among the mountains in the faint
moonlight the grass is singing over the
tumbled graves about the chapel there is
the empty Chapel only poem has no
windows and the door swings dry bones
can harm no one this is my favorite
poems but it doesn't actually mention
Chapel peril of the name it's just the
chapel so I didn't know that I didn't
know of the link until I started
research he's written in his notes
but the wasteland is a post-apocalyptic
poem you have to imagine like 1920s he's
writing in London and everything like
first world war has just finished no one
knows what's going on everything they
used to believe in everything they held
sacred it's gone just the fact that a
war like that could happen has shaken
humanity it's it's a very it's a time
where they're questioning whether they
can ever go back to what they
before or if there is even anything to
go back to as a very like liminal space
and this isn't our Chapel Palace either
although I do like the hymns and the
poem ends with the Shanti Shanti Shanti
which is beautiful
so that bought me thinking about the
word liminal I've always been obsessed
by this word I probably overuse it and
the reason I hope you use it so I learnt
it in University where I studied English
literature it might not surprise you to
hear and I remember being familiar with
the concept and I sort of had an actual
location for the word liminal that made
sense to me and it was here the wood
between the worlds this is from The
Magician's Nephew which is the prequel
to the line of which in the wardrobe in
the nineteen chronicles and so it's a
really beautiful wood it's really dense
like the wild wood and it's described as
the quietest wood you can imagine you
can hear the great trees growing and the
kids when they go in there the human
children who venture into this woods
quickly forget where they came from and
I think it's really apropos that a
vision of a perilous being in a wood
like this it is for me it's sort of
archetypal liminal space and when we in
TS Eliot when he's writing about
Chappell perilous the last of the wild
wood has almost been completely
destroyed because of the industrial
efforts for World War one see how this
lake as as the space where these stories
could afford was destroyed he was still
kind of hoping to find it or looking for
something there and the pools if you
just carry on with me on this journey
and I know it's a little bit a little
bit strange but we'll get there in the
end
so the pools remind me of Robert Anton
Wilson to reality tunnels so this is the
book where I first came across the term
Chappell perilous which was a fortnight
ago and so far since then Robert Anton
Wilson idea of reality tunnels and this
was in his book cosmic trigger which
came out in 1977 are these a perfect I
liked it when people bring reading
material so as you may know the reality
tunnels are kind of like these
through which you see the world but they
also shape your perception they tempt
you with a promise of certainty that's
kind of the siren singing at the end of
it reality tunnel so me they seem quite
um analogous to what Peter talks about
when he talks about mimetic tribes and
interestingly as you'll know if you've
read the book Robert Anton Wilson
describes almost going insane from
immersing himself and all these
contradictory conspiracy theories nasty
tunnels which is is that what Peter
describes well maybe not insane but a
little bit after immersing himself in
the ideology all the different Matic
tribes and I will cast called the sacrum
a skeptic where I get really into all
different New Age subcultures I feel
like I've been on the brink for a little
so well Max and Wilson describes Chapel
perilous at that time when you're
wondering whether what you're perceiving
is real or if it's just in your head
when the map is inadequate for the
territory and this isn't quite our
Chapel perilous either but it's really
close so I think our Chapel perilous
doesn't exist yet I think this is us
building it right now and I think it's
going to incorporate some of the themes
of the previous chapel palaces that do
exist or have existed in literature so I
think there's gonna be it's gonna be
challenging and we're gonna need to be
brave and I know that sounds silly
because this is just talking on the
internet but I think we need to bring
something of that kind of questing
spirit to it I think that as in Alex
Chapel perilous there's gonna be a sense
of disillusionment and perhaps even
morning as we have to let go some things
that seemed like seemed important to us
or seemed like the way things were
perhaps and I hope that there's gonna be
a sense of sort of play and liberation
as in Robert Anton Wilson Chapel
perilous he said Robert Anton Wilson
that is that when you go through trouble
parish you either come out insane or
agnostic and I don't know what's gonna
happen to all of us I don't know what's
gonna happen to me but I'm hoping to
come out different I want to be able to
face uncertainty I've been tempted into
those different reality tunnels and I
want to prevent myself from just
exhausting myself from searching for
that holy grail of like meta mutant
everything will make sense I want to be
to live in this probable universe in a
in an honest way and kind of be okay
with myself at the same time that's my
goal so that's how we all got here now
to continue the metaphor I'm going to
ask you all to step up and make an
offering at the altar of agnosticism
Peter could you turn off the recording
shits about to get real